<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Boom! Michael Droettboom's blog</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://droettboom.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://droettboom.com/</id><updated>2015-11-20T16:16:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Debugging Python C/C++ extensions in gdb</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2015/11/20/gdb-python-extensions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-20T16:16:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-20T16:16:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2015-11-20:/blog/2015/11/20/gdb-python-extensions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; has fantastic support for debugging Python/C extensions.  It
understands how to print the contents of &lt;cite&gt;PyObject *&lt;/cite&gt; variables using
their Python-side representation, and can even print Python
tracebacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These features are described &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Features/EasierPythonDebugging"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;.  I
suggest visiting that link to see why this is so cool.  This blog
posting is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; has fantastic support for debugging Python/C extensions.  It
understands how to print the contents of &lt;cite&gt;PyObject *&lt;/cite&gt; variables using
their Python-side representation, and can even print Python
tracebacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These features are described &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Features/EasierPythonDebugging"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;.  I
suggest visiting that link to see why this is so cool.  This blog
posting is just about how to get those features set up everywhere for
any Python you may have on your system, on any Linux and Mac OS-X, and
some additional tips to help make debugging Python/C extensions in
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="install-the-gdb-python-debugging-extension"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Install the GDB Python-debugging extension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since version 7.0, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; includes an embedded Python interpreter
that can be used to write &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; extensions, changing how variables
and backtraces are displayed.  &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;CPython&lt;/tt&gt; includes one such extension
in its source tree that is useful for debugging Python itself and
Python/C extensions, in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Tools/gdb/libpython.py&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="first admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;First make sure you have a working copy of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt;.  If you're on a
Mac, this process is fairly involved because &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; must be
codesigned.  These &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ntraft.com/installing-gdb-on-os-x-mavericks/"&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt; may be
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usual way for this extension to be used is to install it alongside
the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpythonX.Y.so&lt;/tt&gt; shared object with the special name
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;libpythonX.Y.so-gdb.py&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.  When &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; loads &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython&lt;/tt&gt; it
should then automatically load the extension and start using the
special display hooks for Python.  There are a couple of problems with
this approach: The extension needs to be installed alongside each
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.so&lt;/tt&gt; you want to debug, and if you're like me, you
probably have a bunch of different Python versions installed using
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/yyuu/pyenv"&gt;pyenv&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.continuum.io/downloads"&gt;anaconda&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://brew.sh/"&gt;homebrew&lt;/a&gt;
and the like.  Most of these tools don't install the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; extension
-- the only installation method I know of that actually does this is
Fedora Linux, but even there it only works with the system Python.
Even if we did install this extension alongside each &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.so&lt;/tt&gt;,
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; will only autoload extensions from an explicit whitelist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get around this, we can bypass &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt;'s automatic extension
loading mechanism and have &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/tt&gt; loaded for any
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.so&lt;/tt&gt; you may want to debug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is to obtain the correct version of
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/tt&gt; that matches the embedded Python interpreter inside
of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt;.  This version of Python has &lt;strong&gt;absolutely nothing to do
with&lt;/strong&gt; the version of Python you want to debug -- it is merely the
embedded interpreter that runs &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; extensions.  To see which
version of Python is embedded inside your &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt;, do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
&amp;gt; gdb
GNU gdb (GDB) Fedora 7.10-29.fc23
Copyright (C) 2015 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
License GPLv3+: GNU GPL version 3 or later &amp;lt;http://gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html&amp;gt;
...
(gdb) python
&amp;gt;import sys
&amp;gt;print(sys.version_info)
&amp;gt;end
sys.version_info(major=3, minor=4, micro=3, releaselevel='final', serial=0)
(gdb)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, my embedded Python interpreter is version 3.4.  When I
installed &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdb&lt;/tt&gt; through &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;homebrew&lt;/tt&gt; on my Mac, it had version 2.7.
In both cases, I was able to use this to debug any version of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the version of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/tt&gt; corresponding to the embedded
Python interpreter, and save it somewhere in your home directory.  (I
put it in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;~/.config/gdb/libpython.py&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, but you may want to put it
somewhere else depending on how you organize your configuration
files).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 2.7: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hg.python.org/cpython/rawfile/2.7/Tools/gdb/libpython.py"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 3.3: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hg.python.org/cpython/rawfile/3.3/Tools/gdb/libpython.py"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 3.4: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hg.python.org/cpython/rawfile/3.4/Tools/gdb/libpython.py"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 3.5: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hg.python.org/cpython/rawfile/3.5/Tools/gdb/libpython.py"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we'll set up &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;~/.gdbinit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; to load this extension by adding the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
python
import gdb
import sys
import os
sys.path.insert(0, os.path.expanduser(&amp;quot;~/.emacs.d/gdb&amp;quot;))
def setup_python(event):
    import libpython
gdb.events.new_objfile.connect(setup_python)
end
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to update the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;~/.config/gdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; directory to be the same
directory where you saved &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libpython.py&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you should get nice Python-aware debugging features no matter
which Python you are debugging!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="rebuild-your-extensions-without-optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rebuild your extensions without optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, when debugging, you are seeing missing stack frames or variables
being displayed as &amp;quot;value optimized out&amp;quot;, you'll probably want to
recompile your extension with optimizations turned off.  In the source
directory for your project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
# Completely clear the build directory for good measure
&amp;gt; rm -rf build
&amp;gt; CFLAGS=&amp;quot;-O0 -g&amp;quot; CXXFLAGS=&amp;quot;-O0 -g&amp;quot; python setup.py install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="use-a-debug-build-of-python"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use a debug build of Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've found the above steps to be sufficient for diagnosing most
problems with my own C and C++ Python extensions.  However, in the
rare case where there is some tight interaction between the Python
interpreter and the extension that is causing a problem, it can be
helpful to run the extension in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/devguide/setup.html#compiling-for-debugging"&gt;debug build of Python&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/yyuu/pyenv"&gt;pyenv&lt;/a&gt; provides a convenient way to
build a debug Python.  Just install the version with the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;
suffix:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
&amp;gt; pyenv install 3.5.0-debug
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, extensions built for a regular Python are incompatible
with a debug Python, so your extensions (and its entire stack of
dependencies) will need to be rebuilt, which is why I only suggest
this as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="edits"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Edits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2015-12-03: Fixed errors in gdbinit script.  Fixed links to libpython.py&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="python debugging gdb"></category></entry><entry><title>VirtualBox on Mac OS X</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2013/08/29/virtualbox-on-mac-os-x/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-29T09:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-08-29T09:33:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2013-08-29:/blog/2013/08/29/virtualbox-on-mac-os-x/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently got a Mac Mini so I can start working on Macintosh-specific
issues with matplotlib.  Thanks again to Hans Petter Langtangen, the
Director of the Center for Biomedical Computing at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://home.simula.no/~hpl"&gt;Simula&lt;/a&gt; for his gracious donation that
supported the purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I'd like to use this machine …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently got a Mac Mini so I can start working on Macintosh-specific
issues with matplotlib.  Thanks again to Hans Petter Langtangen, the
Director of the Center for Biomedical Computing at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://home.simula.no/~hpl"&gt;Simula&lt;/a&gt; for his gracious donation that
supported the purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I'd like to use this machine for is to test
installers in various environments -- a fresh install, or with
MacPorts, or Fink etc. -- to make sure the installers include
everything they need.  So I want to run Mac OS X in a virtual machine
that I can reset on a regular basis to a known state.  This is now
allowed by the licensing of OS X, as long as it's running on top of
genuine Apple hardware, and you create no more than 5 instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's surprisingly hard to find information on installing Mac OS X in a
virtual machine.  Most of what Google finds is various hacks to run on
non-Apple hardware.  I, instead, want to do this legally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Mac Mini came with no installation media, so you
can't just plug it in and install it in a virtual machine.  I thought,
ok, no problem -- I'll just pop over to the App Store and download it.
Unfortunately, to do that, Apple wanted to charge me $29.99 for
something I already own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So next I looked at the recovery partition.  Parallels is reportedly
able to use the recovery partition directly to install in the virtual
machine.  However, I want to use VirtualBox, since it is open source,
what I'm familiar with on Linux, and, most importantly, because it can
be automated by vagrant.  After trying in vain to point VirtualBox at
the magic stuff in the recovery partition, I came upon a working
solution.  The following steps were done with Mountain Lion, and I
have no idea whether they are applicable to other releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Grab an external USB drive and plug it in.  I think it needs to be
at least the size of a double-layer DVD, or 8.5 GB.  This process
will erase everything on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Reboot into recovery mode, by holding down Command+R during boot.  (A word
of advice to those new to Macs: wait until you hear the startup sound until
you press the keys down, and hold them until the Apple logo disappears.
Timing seems to be important here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;I list of utilities will appear.  Open &amp;quot;Disk Manager&amp;quot; and
repartition the external disk to have a &amp;quot;GUID&amp;quot; partition table with
a single &amp;quot;HFS+&amp;quot; partition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Exit &amp;quot;Disk Manager&amp;quot; and then go to &amp;quot;Install OS X&amp;quot;.  Install it to the
external drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;When the installation is done, the system will reboot back into your &amp;quot;host&amp;quot;
installation on the internal drive.  (I was surprised by this -- you may
need to remove the USB drive to boot into the internal drive, but I didn't
need to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The result is a folder on the external drive called &amp;quot;OS X Install
Data&amp;quot;.  Inside that folder is a disk image of the installer,
&lt;cite&gt;InstallESD.dmg&lt;/cite&gt;.  Copy this to your internal hard disk.  You can
then remove the external USB drive, we're done with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Unfortunately, there is still a small incompatibility with power
management inside of VirtualBox that will cause the installer to
hang during boot.  The kernel extension that handles CPU power
management needs to be replaced.  I found the instructions for that
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ntk.me/2012/09/07/os-x-on-os-x/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  I'm paraphrasing
it here, and only including instructions for Mountain Lion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Download &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ntkme/InstallESD.dmg.tool"&gt;InstallESD.dmg.tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Download NullCPUPowerManagement.kext&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Run the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
./InstallESD.dmg.tool -i InstallESD.dmg -o Output.dmg -- NullCPUPowerManagement.kext
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The &lt;cite&gt;Output.dmg&lt;/cite&gt; is now a patched installer image that can be used
to install OS X in VirtualBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;In VirtualBox, create a new virtual machine and use its default
settings for an OS X guest.  Then, open the settings for the machine
and go to the Storage tab.  Add a new CD/DVD device to the IDE bus
(it must be IDE: SATA did not work for me), and select the
Output.dmg from the file dialog.  Check the &amp;quot;Live CD/DVD&amp;quot; box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;You now should be able to boot into the installer and install OS X
within VirtualBox.  When the installer is ready to reboot, go back
to VirtualBox settings and &amp;quot;eject&amp;quot; the virtual DVD before restarting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this will help others out.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>matplotlib lessons learned</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2013/03/25/matplotlib-lessons-learned/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-25T09:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-03-25T09:47:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2013-03-25:/blog/2013/03/25/matplotlib-lessons-learned/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jake Vanderplass has a very thought-provoking essay about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jakevdp.github.com/blog/2013/03/23/matplotlib-and-the-future-of-visualization-in-python/"&gt;future
of visualization in Python&lt;/a&gt;.
It's an exciting time for visualization in Python with so many new
options exploding onto the scene, and Jake has provided a nice
summary.  However, I don't think it presents a very current view of
matplotlib …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jake Vanderplass has a very thought-provoking essay about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jakevdp.github.com/blog/2013/03/23/matplotlib-and-the-future-of-visualization-in-python/"&gt;future
of visualization in Python&lt;/a&gt;.
It's an exciting time for visualization in Python with so many new
options exploding onto the scene, and Jake has provided a nice
summary.  However, I don't think it presents a very current view of
matplotlib, which is still alive and well with funding sources, and
moving to &amp;quot;modern&amp;quot; things like web frontends and web services, and has
nascent ongoing project related to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rougier/gl-agg"&gt;hardware acceleration&lt;/a&gt;.  Importantly, it has thousands
of person hours of investment in all of the large to tiny problems
that have been found along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="in-the-browser"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In the browser&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the directions that new plotting projects are taking is to be
more integrated in the web browser.  This has all of the advantages of
cloud computing (zero install, distributed data), and integrates well
with great projects like the IPython notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;matplotlib is already most of the way there.  matplotlib's git master
has completely interactive and full featured plotting in the browser
-- meaning it can do everything any of the other matplotlib backends
can do -- by basically running something very similar to a VNC
protocol between the server and the client. You can try it out today
by building from git and using the WebAgg backend. Shortly, it will
also be available as part of Google App Engine -- so we'll get some
real experience running these things remotely in a real
&amp;quot;Internet-enabled&amp;quot; mode. The integration work with IPython still needs
to be done -- and I hope this can be a major focus of discussion at
SciPy when I'm there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The VNC-like approach was ultimately arrived at after many months of
experimenting with approaches more based on JS and HTML5 and/or
SVG. The main problem one runs into with those approaches is working
with large datasets -- matplotlib has some very sophisticated designs
to make working working with large data sets zippy and interactive
(specifically path simplification, blitting of markers, dynamic down
sampling of images) all of which are just really hard to implement
efficiently in a browser. D3's Javascript demos feel very zippy and
efficient, until you realize how canned they are, or how much they
rely on very specific means to shuttle reduced data and from the
browser.  There's a place for interactive canned graphics as part of
web publishing, but it's much less useful for doing science on data
for the first time.  But in general from these experiments, I've become
rather skeptical of approaches that try to do too much in the
browser. Even though matplotlib is on the &amp;quot;old&amp;quot; paradigm of running on
a server (or a local desktop), the advantage of that approach is that
we control the whole stack and can optimize the heck out of the places
that need to be optimized. Browsers are much more of a black box in
that regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know if WebGL will offer some improvements here.  It's enough
of a moving target that it should probably be re-examined on a regular
basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="on-the-gpu"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On the GPU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the diametrically opposite direction, we have projects moving
plotting onto the GPU.  Particularly interesting to me here is the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rougier/gl-agg"&gt;glagg&lt;/a&gt; project by Nicolas
Rougier and others.  It's important to note for those not in the
trenches that for high-quality 2D plotting on the GPU, things are much
less straightforward than for 3D.  Graphics cards don't &amp;quot;just do&amp;quot;
high-quality 2D rendering out of the box.  It requires the use of
custom vertex shaders (which are frankly works of extreme brilliance
and also an exercise somewhat in putting round pegs in square holes
and living to tell about it).  Unfortunately, these things require
rather recent graphics hardware and drivers and a fair bit of patience
to get up and running.  Things will get easier over time, but at the
moment, a 100% software implementation still can't be beat for
portability and maximum accessibility for less technically-inclined
users.  But I look forward to where all of this is going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real benchmarking on real data needs to be performed to determine just
how much faster these approaches will be for 2D plotting.  (For 3D,
which I discuss below, I think the advantages of hardware are more
apparent).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="first admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;As a public service announcement, anyone looking for performance out
of matplotlib should be using the Agg backend -- it's the only one
with all optimizations available.  The Mac OS-X Quartz backend is
built on a closed source rendering library with some puzzling and
surprising performance characteristics.  Many of the attempts to
speed up that backend involve workarounds for a black box that is
not well understood.  For the Agg-based backends, however, we
control the stack from top-to-bottom and are able to optimize for
real-world scientific plotting scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="in-3-dimensions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In 3-dimensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;matplotlib's original focus has always been on 2D.  Despite this,
notably Benjamin Root and others continue to put a lot of effort into
matplotlib's 3D extensions, and they fill a niche for many users who
want clean and crisp vector 3D for print, and it's improving all the
time.  There are, of course, fundamental architectural problems with
3D in matplotlib (most importantly the lack of a proper z-ordering)
that limit what can be done.  That should be fixable with a few
well-placed C/C++ extensions -- I'm not certain that we need go whole
hog to the GPU to fix that, but that's certainly the obvious and
well-trodden solution.  I am concerned that too many of the new 3D
projects seem to prioritize interactivity and hardware tricks at the
expense of static quality.  For this reason, matplotlib may continue
to serve for some time as a high-quality print &amp;quot;backend&amp;quot; for some of
these other 3-D based projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="interfaces"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interfaces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting direction of experimentation is in the area of
user interface and API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think matplotlib owes a lot of its success to its shameless
&amp;quot;embracing and extending&amp;quot; of the Matlab graphing API.  Having taught
matplotlib a few times to new users, I'm always impressed by how
quickly new users pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that's a but cruftier and full of inconsistencies is
matplotlib's Object-Oriented interface.  Things there often follow the
pattern that was most easy to implement rather than what would be the
most clean from the outside.  It's probably due time to start
re-evaluating some of those API's and breaking backward compatibility
for the sake of more consistency going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cs.uic.edu/~wilkinson/TheGrammarOfGraphics/GOG.html"&gt;Grammar of Graphics&lt;/a&gt;
syntax from the R world is really interesting, and I think fills a
middle ground.  It's more powerful (and I think a little more complex
to learn at first) than the Matlab interface, but it has the nice
property of self-consistency that once you learn a few things you can
easily guess at how to do many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Wang's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/continuumio/bokeh"&gt;Bokeh&lt;/a&gt; project
aims to bring Grammar of Graphics to Python, which I think is very
cool.  Note however, that even there, Bokeh includes a matlab-like
interface, as does another plotting project &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rossant/galry"&gt;Galry&lt;/a&gt;, so mlab is by no means dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="doomed-to-repeat"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Doomed to repeat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of ways in which matplotlib can be improved.  I
encourage everyone to look at our &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/matplotlib/matplotlib/wiki"&gt;MEPS&lt;/a&gt; to see some ongoing
projects that are being discussed or worked on.  There are some large,
heroic and important projects there to bring matplotlib forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think more interestingly for this blog post is to focus on some
of the really low-level early architectural decisions that have
limited or made it difficult to move matplotlib forward.  Importantly,
these aren't issues that I'm seeing discussed very often, but they are
things I would try to tackle up front if I ever get a case of
&amp;quot;2.0-itis&amp;quot; and were starting fresh today.  Hopefully these injuries of
experience can inform new projects -- or they may inspire someone with
loads of time to take on refactoring matplotlib.  It would not be
impossible to make these changes to matplotlib, but it would take a
concerted long-term effort and the ability to break some backward
compatibility for the common good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="generic-tree-manipulations"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Generic tree manipulations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;matplotlib plots are more-or-less tree structures of objects that are
&amp;quot;run&amp;quot; to draw things on the screen.  (It isn't strictly a tree, as
some cross-referencing is required for things like referring to clip
paths etc.)  For example, the figure has any number of axes, each of
which have lines plotted on them.  Drawing involves starting at the
figure and visiting each of its axes and each of its lines.  All very
straightforward.  But there is no way to traverse that tree in a
generic way to perform manipulations on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you might want to have a plot with a number of
different-colored lines that you want to make ready for
black-and-white publication by changing the lines to have different
dash patterns.  Or, you might want to go through all of the text and
change the font.  Or, as much as it personally wouldn't fit my
workflow, many people would like a graphical editor that would allow
one to traverse the tree of objects in the plot and change properties
on them.  There's currently no way to do this in a generic way that
would work on any plot with any kind of object in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm thinking what is needed is something like the much-maligned
&amp;quot;Document Object Model (DOM)&amp;quot; is needed (if I say &amp;quot;ElementTree&amp;quot;
instead, is that more appealing to Pythonistas?)  That way, one could
traverse this tree in a generic fashion and do all kinds of things
without needing to be aware of what specifically is in the plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="type-checking-styles-properties-traits"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Type-checking, styles, properties, traits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;matplotlib predates properties and traits and other things of that
ilk, so it, not unreasonably, uses &lt;cite&gt;get_&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;set_&lt;/cite&gt; methods for most
things.  Beyond the syntactic implications of this (which don't bother
me as much as some), they are rather inconsistent.  Some are available
as keyword arguments to constructors and plotting methods, but it's
inconsistent because some must be manually handled by the code while
others are handled automatically.  Some type-check their arguments
immediately, whereas others will blow up on invalid input much later
in some deeply nested backtrace.  Some are mutable and cause an update
of the plot when changed.  Some seem mutable, but changing them has no
effect.  Traits (such as Enthought Traits or something else in that
space) would be a great fit for this.  It's been examined a few times,
and while the idea seems to be a good fit, the implementation was
always the stumbling block.  But it's high time to look at this again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining this with the tree manipulation suggestion above, we'd be
able to do really powerful things like CSS-style styling of plots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Didn't I just say above that web browsers weren't well suited, yet
I'm stealing some fundamentals of their design here...?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to the above, matplotlib's handling of colors and
alpha-blending is all over the map.  There needs to be a cleanup
effort to make handling consistent throughout.  Once that's done, the
way forward should be clear to manage CMYK colors internally for
formats that support them (e.g. PDF).  Ditto on other properties like
line styles and marker styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="projections-and-ticking"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Projections and ticking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ticking is the process by which the positions of the grid lines, ticks
and labels are determined.  There are a number of third-party projects
that build new projections on top of matplotlib (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matplotlib.org/basemap/"&gt;basemap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://leejjoon.github.com/pywcsgrid2/"&gt;pywcsgrid2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scitools.org.uk/cartopy/"&gt;cartopy&lt;/a&gt; to name a few).  Unfortunately,
they can't really take advantage of the many (and subtly difficult)
ticking algorithms in matplotlib because matplotlib's tickers are so
firmly grounded in the rectilinear world.  matplotlib needs to improve
its tickers to be more generic and more usable when the grid is
rotated or warped in a myriad of ways so that all of this duplication
of effort can be reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to this, matplotlib have transformations (which determine how
the data is mapped to the Cartesian space on screen), tickers (which
determine the positions of grid lines), formatters (which determine
how the tick's text label is rendered) and locators (which choose
pleasant-looking bounds for the data), all of which work in tandem to
produce the labels, ticks and gridlines, but which have no
relationship to each other.  It should be easier to relate these
things together, because you usually want a set that works well
together.  Phil Elson has done some work in this direction, but
there's still more that could be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="higher-dimensionality"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Higher dimensionality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;matplotlib's 3D support feels tacked on structurally.  It would be
better if more parts were agnostic to the dimensionality of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="may-you-live-in-interesting-times"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May you live in interesting times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's really exciting to watch all that's going on, and thanks to Jake
Vanderplass for getting this discussion rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="matplotlib"></category></entry><entry><title>Matplotlib in the browser: It's coming</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2012/10/11/matplotlib-in-the-browser-its-coming/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-11T14:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-10-11T14:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2012-10-11:/blog/2012/10/11/matplotlib-in-the-browser-its-coming/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote class="pull-quote"&gt;
UPDATE: I am now sharing my code in the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mdboom/mpl_browser_experiments"&gt;mdboom/mpl_browser_experiments&lt;/a&gt; github
repository, rather than in a gist.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's occurred to me recently that in my previous blog posts &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdboom.github.com/blog/2012/08/07/client-side-rendering-in-matplotlib/"&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdboom.github.com/blog/2012/08/06/matplotlib-client-side/"&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;,
I was going about the problem all wrong.  Getting the plotting logic
running in the browser …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote class="pull-quote"&gt;
UPDATE: I am now sharing my code in the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mdboom/mpl_browser_experiments"&gt;mdboom/mpl_browser_experiments&lt;/a&gt; github
repository, rather than in a gist.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's occurred to me recently that in my previous blog posts &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdboom.github.com/blog/2012/08/07/client-side-rendering-in-matplotlib/"&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdboom.github.com/blog/2012/08/06/matplotlib-client-side/"&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;,
I was going about the problem all wrong.  Getting the plotting logic
running in the browser, while perhaps ideal, was full of pitfalls.
The browsers all render things in different ways and have different
performance characteristics.  Large data structures in Javascript just
start to fall over after a certain point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One effective way to deal with the large data structure problem is to
just not send them to the browser at all, but instead, send rendered
images.  While the size of the data scientists will want to process
with Numpy and matplotlib is growing all the time, the size of the
images being rendered have natural limits based on the resolution of
our displays. (Retina displays have recently bumped this up, but even
then, display resolution increases slowly relative to RAM and disk
space).  So while for simple plots, sending and using the data wins,
for anything beyond a reasonable amount of complexity, sending
rendering images beats it (in terms of bandwidth) every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other advantage of this approach is that it will work &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt;
like regular matplotlib.  All of the effort and work that has already
gone into matplotlib to make it as feature-rich and pixel-perfect as
it is will apply immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started to look at how we could just pipe what we already have --
a high-quality, fast, and extensive rendering framework based on &lt;a class="reference external" href="www.antigrain.com"&gt;Agg&lt;/a&gt; -- into the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="experiments-with-vnc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experiments with VNC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An obvious pre-existing hammer on the shelf was &lt;cite&gt;VNC
&amp;lt;www.realvnc.com&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;.  There are free servers available for all of the
big platforms, and there is, believe it or not, a client written
entirely in Javascript that runs in the browser: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kanaka.github.com/noVNC/"&gt;noVNC&lt;/a&gt;.  After a little tinkering (I'll
spare you the details), it's possible to share a single GUI window in
the matplotlib kernel with a browser.  And it works, more or less,
although a little slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few problems with using VNC (and this mostly applies to its
competitor NX as well):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VNC servers hook directly into the GUI technology of your
platform, so each platform handles setting up a server rather
differently.  I'm always loathe to reach for solutions that
involve a lot of platform-specific differences -- it becomes a
nightmare to support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a lot of unnecessary moving pieces.  On X11, for
example, the VNC wants to be an entire X server, with a window
manager etc.  The window being shared, of course, has to be
implemented in some GUI framework or other.  That's a lot of
extra stuff to install on a headless server that we don't really
need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;cite&gt;noVNC&lt;/cite&gt; client has to interpret the binary VNC protocol &lt;em&gt;in
Javascript&lt;/em&gt;.  Joel Martin and the rest of the team are total
rockstars and they've pulled off something very impressive.  But
at the end of the day, it's not a great fit, and it wastes a lot
of cycles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So VNC almost gets us there, and the fact that it works &amp;quot;almost well
enough&amp;quot; gave me confidence that a more &amp;quot;conduit&amp;quot;-based approach would
work.  So I got to thinking about what the bare minimum thing is that
could work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact is that VNC, at least as it was being used in the above
context, is just sending events from the keyboard and mouse from the
client, and getting delta images from the server.  It has a rather
sophisticated way of compressing those delta images, but at the end of
the day, that's all it really does for us, and all we really need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that creating delta images in PNG doesn't work too badly.
The empty pixels compress away rather well, and the compression and
decompression can be handled in C at both ends of the pipe.  That is,
browsers know how to decompress PNGs inherently -- they don't need to
run slow and complex Javascript to do so, so while it may not be the
optimal protocol, it's a good choice in a practical sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-proof-of-concept"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A proof of concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mdboom/mpl_browser_experiments"&gt;in this repository&lt;/a&gt;, I present a
proof-of-concept for this approach.  I have some hideously rough and
undocumented code that, given a matplotlib figure, serves it
interactively to a web browser.  It requires only matplotlib and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tornadoweb.org/"&gt;Tornado&lt;/a&gt; (which you probably already
have if you already have a recent IPython).  It's obviously a long way
from here to something that's a true matplotlib backend and
well-integrated with IPython notebook.  This code in no way represents
the final API.  I also don't do a lot of network programming, so I may
be handling the AJAXy things suboptimally.  However, I'd appreciate
testing of this approach on different platforms and browsers to just
prove its feasibility before putting in too much of that follow-on
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use it, just create a matplotlib figure, with whatever you want,
and pass it to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;serve_figure.serve_figure()&lt;/tt&gt;.  For example, take the
quadmesh example (something that would be really hard to implement in
HTML5 canvas) and serve it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
import serve_figure

import numpy as np
from numpy import ma
from matplotlib import pyplot as plt

n = 12
x = np.linspace(-1.5,1.5,n)
y = np.linspace(-1.5,1.5,n*2)
X,Y = np.meshgrid(x,y);
Qx = np.cos(Y) - np.cos(X)
Qz = np.sin(Y) + np.sin(X)
Qx = (Qx + 1.1)
Z = np.sqrt(X**2 + Y**2)/5;
Z = (Z - Z.min()) / (Z.max() - Z.min())

# The color array can include masked values:
Zm = ma.masked_where(np.fabs(Qz) &amp;lt; 0.5*np.amax(Qz), Z)

fig = plt.figure()
ax = fig.add_subplot(121)
ax.set_axis_bgcolor(&amp;quot;#bdb76b&amp;quot;)
ax.pcolormesh(Qx,Qz,Z, shading='gouraud')
ax.set_title('Without masked values')

ax = fig.add_subplot(122)
ax.set_axis_bgcolor(&amp;quot;#bdb76b&amp;quot;)
col = ax.pcolormesh(Qx,Qz,Zm,shading='gouraud')
ax.set_title('With masked values')

serve_figure.serve_figure(fig, port=8888)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open up your webbrowser to &lt;cite&gt;http://127.0.0.1:8888&lt;/cite&gt; and you should
(hopefully) be in business.  Open up a second browser window (whether
locally or on another machine) and note that the two plots are
automatically synchronized.  The &amp;quot;data cursor&amp;quot; (that displays the
current location of the mouse cursor in data coordinates) also works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://mdboom.github.com/images/firefox.png" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Matplotlib running in Firefox&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some back-of-the-napkin thoughts about performance: The average size
of each frame at the default resolution is around 16 kbytes.  On a
standard 1MB DSL connection, we should be able to pipe 7000 of those
per second, so it should be fine in terms of bandwidth.  Of course,
there are other factors, such as the latency of the network and the
CPU time necessary to decompress the PNG files etc. that are harder to
take account of.  This will require some real-world testing to really
get a sense of how well it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of finesse to follow.  For example, we should be able to
shrink the bandwidth by another 20% by using a 1-bit alpha channel.
The cursor shape doesn't ever change like it does in a regular
matplotlib window.  It should be possible (though not yet) to support
the interactive callbacks in matplotlib to handle the mouse events in
arbitrary ways inside of the server.  In principle, there are very few
limitations to this approach, and it has the potential to be a true
peer to the existing backends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the matplotlib and IPython projects -- pull requests will be
coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Amazon MP3 ends their support for Linux</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2012/09/11/amazon-mp3-ends-their-support-for-linux/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-09-11T11:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-09-11T11:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2012-09-11:/blog/2012/09/11/amazon-mp3-ends-their-support-for-linux/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've bought digital music from Amazon for almost as long as they've
been in that business.  Their prices are very competitive, the MP3's
are dog-standard and DRM-free so they work on every device imaginable,
and, until recently, they have supported Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, they haven't supported Linux well for some time …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've bought digital music from Amazon for almost as long as they've
been in that business.  Their prices are very competitive, the MP3's
are dog-standard and DRM-free so they work on every device imaginable,
and, until recently, they have supported Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, they haven't supported Linux well for some time.  Their
own downloading app (when it was available) had fallen into disrepair
and didn't work on most modern Linux distributions.  However, the
simple, yet effective, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/p/clamz/"&gt;clamz&lt;/a&gt;
filled that void quite nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, however, when you try to download more than one file at a time,
you're greeted with this message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
On Linux systems, Cloud Player only supports downloading songs one
at a time. To download your music, deselect all checkboxes, select
the checkbox for the song you want to download, then click the
&amp;quot;Download&amp;quot; button.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing the User Agent string and/or deleting cookies doesn't seem to
get over the wall.  Other clamz users don't appear to have &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/p/clamz/issues/detail?id=35"&gt;any
solutions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I contacted Amazon customer support to confirm that there was
truly no workaround, the reply was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
I am sorry to know that you are not able to download multiple
songs from the cloud player. To download multiple songs you will
need the Amazon MP3 downloader. However since you are using a
Linux operating system, you will need to download one song at a
time from the cloud player.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we have always been at war with Eastasia.  And you've never
been able to purchase and download MP3's from Amazon on a Linux box.
The hundreds of dollars I've spent doing just that certainly don't
mean anything.  Thankfully, since it's all DRM-free they can't take
away what I already have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, Amazon, but I'm not a clicking monkey.  I'll need to go
elsewhere.  Can anyone else recommend another DRM-free service that
doesn't require jumping through so many hoops to download purchases?&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>John Hunter</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2012/08/31/john-hunter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-31T10:22:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-31T10:22:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2012-08-31:/blog/2012/08/31/john-hunter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have lost one of the greats of our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first met John Hunter when he came to give a presentation about
matplotlib at the Space Telescope Science Institute in 2004 (or
thereabouts).  I remember being blown away by how capable matplotlib
was (even then), and stunned by John's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have lost one of the greats of our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first met John Hunter when he came to give a presentation about
matplotlib at the Space Telescope Science Institute in 2004 (or
thereabouts).  I remember being blown away by how capable matplotlib
was (even then), and stunned by John's drive to build it completely
outside of what was paying the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years later, when I started working at STScI in 2007, one of my first
tasks was to add some new features to matplotlib.  Little did I know,
it would become my passion as well.  I was a little intimidated to be
working on something so entrenched and widely used.  But John somehow
instilled confidence in me with his support of what I was doing, even
as I was ripping apart old assumptions in the code and turning it over
anew.  Through all the e-mails, conference calls and chance conference
meetings with John since, he has been the most encouraging mentor and
a prime example of open source stewardship.  I should be lucky to find
even a fraction of the enthusiasm, skill and leadership that John had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally impressive has been watching so many of us Scientific Python
types, separated by geography and institutional affiliations, come
together in supporting each other at a time like this.  Sometimes it
really is more than just code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If matplotlib has been useful to you in any way, please give
generously to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.org/johnhunter/"&gt;John Hunter Memorial Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Client-side Rendering in Matplotlib, Part II: The language blender</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2012/08/07/client-side-rendering-in-matplotlib/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-07T13:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-07T13:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2012-08-07:/blog/2012/08/07/client-side-rendering-in-matplotlib/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="first admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;EDIT 2012-08-08: Added benchmarks in Firefox in addition to Chrome&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdboom.github.com/blog/2012/08/06/matplotlib-client-side/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;,
I outlined some of the architectural difficulties bringing
matplotlib's interactivity to the browser.  In short, there's a big
chunk of code that lies between building the tree of artists and
rendering them to the screen …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="first admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;EDIT 2012-08-08: Added benchmarks in Firefox in addition to Chrome&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdboom.github.com/blog/2012/08/06/matplotlib-client-side/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;,
I outlined some of the architectural difficulties bringing
matplotlib's interactivity to the browser.  In short, there's a big
chunk of code that lies between building the tree of artists and
rendering them to the screen that needs to run either in the Python
interpreter, as it does now, or inside of the web browser to support
interactive web applications.  It would be great to avoid having two
code bases, one in Python and one in Javascript, that would need to be
kept in sync.  Writing code for both contexts from a single code base
may turn out to be a pipe dream, but bear with me as I explore tools
that might help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, when trying to grok the discussion here and understanding the
architectural challenges of matplotlib, it may be helpful to read the
matplotlib chapter by John Hunter and yours truly from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.aosabook.org/en/index.html"&gt;Architecture
of Open Source Applications, Volume II&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="tools"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few interesting projects that help bridge the gap between
Python and Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pyjs"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PyJs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pyjs.org"&gt;PyJs&lt;/a&gt; (formerly called Pyjamas) is a
Python-to-Javascript converter.  It also includes an environment much
like Google Web Toolkits for developing rich client-side applications
in Python, but those features are probably not useful here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="skulpt"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Skulpt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.skulpt.org"&gt;Skulpt&lt;/a&gt; is a Python interpreter written in
Javascript.  It can compile and run Python code entirely within the
web browser.  In terms of language features, it doesn't seem as mature
as PyJs, but the fact that it has no dependencies other than a couple
of Javascript files may be an advantage in terms of deployment.  An
obvious shortcoming of both Skulpt and PyJs is the lack of support for
Numpy -- none of the existing matplotlib Python code, which depends so
heavily on Numpy, would work in that context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pyv8"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PyV8&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the other two, which allow Python to run in the browser, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/p/pyv8/"&gt;PyV8&lt;/a&gt; allows Javascript to run inside of
the Python interpreter.  It is a wrapper around Google's open source
V8 Javascript engine and allows sharing objects between Python and
Javascript somewhat transparently.  If the drawing code were to be
rewritten in Javascript, it could then, theoretically, be used both
from Python on the desktop and inside the web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="playing-around"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Playing around&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a first pass playing with these tools, I've created a new project
on github &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mdboom/py-js-blending-experiments"&gt;py-js-blending-experiments&lt;/a&gt;.  I've
started by writing a very simple benchmark that does a simple 2D
affine transformation, in pure Python, Python with Numpy, Javascript
and C.  This test, while a real-world bottleneck from the real-world
matplotlib, is probably too simple to read too much into the results.
A real test would involve classes with complex interactions between
them, to show how the same flexible system of transformations,
tickers, formatters etc. would work, and would take into account the
penalty of stepping over the gap between Python and Javascript.  But
all that will have to wait for a future blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The benchmarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benchmarks compare a number of different possible approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pure Python&lt;/strong&gt;: This is just a simple pure Python implementation.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://raw.github.com/mdboom/py-js-blending-experiments/master/transform.py"&gt;transform.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pure Javascript&lt;/strong&gt;: A hand-written JavaScript implementation.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://raw.github.com/mdboom/py-js-blending-experiments/master/transform.js"&gt;transform.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Numpy&lt;/strong&gt;: An implementation using vectorized Numpy operations.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://raw.github.com/mdboom/py-js-blending-experiments/master/transform_numpy.py"&gt;transform_numpy.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C extension&lt;/strong&gt;: A hand-written C extension.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://raw.github.com/mdboom/py-js-blending-experiments/master/transform.c"&gt;transform.c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skulpt&lt;/strong&gt;: Taking the pure Python implementation above, but running through
Skulpt to get it to run inside of the browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyJs&lt;/strong&gt;: Compiling the pure Python implementation above to
Javascipt using PyJs, and then running the result in the browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyV8&lt;/strong&gt;: Running the hand-written Javascript implementation above
inside of PyV8.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="results"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following results are on a quad-core Intel Core i5-2520M CPU &amp;#64;
2.50GHz running Fedora Linux 17.  Python 2.7.3, Numpy 1.6.1, Google
Chrome 21.0.1180.57 beta and Firefox 14.0.1 were used.  The benchmark
is performing a 2D affine transformation on 128,000 points.  Note that
the timings in the web browser are quite variable.  I've included the
average and independent results of 5 runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
=========================== ================== ==================================
Benchmark                   avg. time (in ms)  times
=========================== ================== ==================================
Pure Python                 94                 95, 96, 93, 96, 92
Pure Javascript Chrome      40                 41, 29, 59, 33, 42
Pure Javascript Firefox     15                 8, 7, 25, 20, 16
Numpy                       6                  7, 6, 6, 6, 6
C                           2                  2, 2, 2, 2, 2
Skulpt Chrome               686                700, 691, 676, 691, 676
Skulpt Firefox              1052               1027, 1052, 1062, 1060, 1061
PyJs Chrome                 2197               2156, 2218, 2176, 2187, 2251
PyJs Firefox                658                644, 687, 630, 680, 674
PyV8                        38                 38, 38, 38, 37, 37
=========================== ================== ==================================
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can we conclude?  Remember what I said about not reading too
much into these results?  Well, I'm going to do it anyway with an
enormous caveat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is considerable overhead when trying to shoehorn Python into the
browser (comparing Skulpt and PyJs to Pure Javascript).  I personally
am surprised by how much more successful the Python interpreter
approach is vs. the Python to Javascript conversion approach, though
that may be due to the relative incompleteness of Skulpt.  (&lt;em&gt;EDIT:
Though the Firefox results tell the opposite story&lt;/em&gt;). It's pretty
clear where the overhead of PyJs comes from.  The line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
X = a*x + c*y + e
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;converts to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
X = $p['__op_add']($add3=$p['__op_add']($add1=(typeof ($mul1=a)==typeof ($mul2=x) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; typeof $mul1=='number'?
    $mul1*$mul2:
    $p['op_mul']($mul1,$mul2)),$add2=(typeof ($mul3=c)==typeof ($mul4=y) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; typeof $mul3=='number'?
    $mul3*$mul4:
    $p['op_mul']($mul3,$mul4))),$add4=e);
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see how basic numeric operators in Python don't translate
directly to those in Javascript, so it's forced to do something a
whole lot more dynamic, including typechecking within every loop
iteration.  I pity the fool Javascript engine that tries to optimize
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, the PyV8 engine performs comparably to the V8 engine
embedded in Google Chrome, which also beats pure Python by at least a
factor of 2.  We could do rather well implementing this core in
Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numpy and C extensions, of course, beat everything handily for this
very numerically-biased benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where does that leave us?  Who knows...  Interesting ride, though.
Stay tuned and leave comments...  There's more to hack away at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="matplotlib"></category></entry><entry><title>Client-side rendering in matplotlib, Part I: Defining the problem</title><link href="http://droettboom.com/blog/2012/08/06/matplotlib-client-side/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-06T16:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-06T16:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael Droettboom</name></author><id>tag:droettboom.com,2012-08-06:/blog/2012/08/06/matplotlib-client-side/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the big challenges that matplotlib faces as it enters its
second decade is moving from a desktop app to the web browser
client/server paradigm.  This need has been known for a few years at
least: SAGE and the IPython notebook are rich web clients and powerful
ways …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the big challenges that matplotlib faces as it enters its
second decade is moving from a desktop app to the web browser
client/server paradigm.  This need has been known for a few years at
least: SAGE and the IPython notebook are rich web clients and powerful
ways to interact with Python, however, their plotting is still
necessarily limited by matplotlib's design to rendering a static
image.  John Hunter concluded his keynote at SciPy 2012 arguing that
this was the single biggest challenge to matplotlib's relevance today.&lt;/p&gt;
{% video http://veyepar.nextdayvideo.com/site_media/static/veyepar//enthought/scipy_2012/mp4/matplotlib_lessons_middle_age.mp4 %}&lt;p&gt;The performance of JavaScript and graphics in web browsers is no
longer an issue.  At least on a gut level, it appears to compete well
with anything matplotlib is able to do with its Python bindings to
traditional desktop GUI toolkits.  See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;d3&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/p/webgl-surface-plot/"&gt;webgl-surface-plot&lt;/a&gt;
for some examples of great, high-performance plotting coming out of
the JavaScript community.  The problem with those libraries is they
don't integrate well with Python data processing, they are harder to
modify and extend and, let's be honest, just generally lack the
Pythonic features that have made matplotlib so popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When trying to determine how to pull matplotlib kicking and screaming
into this Brave New World, let's assume that the network bottleneck
between the server (e.g. an IPython kernel) and the client (i.e. the
web browser) is too high to simply send images over repeatedly.  It
would be awfully nice, if we're going to do all this work anyway, to
allow for interacting with a server that may be over a slow and
high-latency internet connection on the other side of the globe.  The
only way to make interactivity bearable in that scenario is to put
some actual plotting smarts into the client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this discussion, we should define what
interactivity means.  I think it basically amounts to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data cursor (i.e. getting the current position of the mouse in
data coordinates)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;panning and zooming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adjusting the edges of the axes within the figure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other interactive features, such as a &amp;quot;back&amp;quot; button or &amp;quot;apply tight
layout&amp;quot; button have an &amp;quot;activate and return&amp;quot; interaction, rather than
real time interaction, so can probably be handled with a round-trip to
the server and thus aren't really considered here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's well known that matplotlib has a number of backends that handle
drawing to specific GUI frameworks or file formats.  The matplotlib
&amp;quot;core&amp;quot; understands how to build and generate plots, and then sends
low-level drawing commands to the currently selected backend.  In
order to reduce code duplication, there is a solid wall between the
core and the backends, and we're constantly trying to minimize the
amount of code required to write a backend.  The advantage of this is
not just to reduce the number of lines of code, but to ensure
consistency between the backends, so that when you render a streamplot
with hatching and custom markers to a PDF file, it looks the same as
when you render it to an SVG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why can't we just add a new &amp;quot;webbrowser&amp;quot; backend?  The problem is
that the backends are too low-level.  They know where the shapes and
the text are, but they know nothing how they relate to one another,
how the data scales from its native data coordinates to the
coordinates of the screen, and how to best add ticks and other
annotations to the graph.  All of that information would be required
for any sort of interactivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To even begin to tackle this, we need to move from the current two-way
split of the plotting core and rendering backends to a three-way split
into the phases of outputting a plot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt;: This phase is where the various Artist objects that
make up the plot are created and related to one another.  This is
where most of the domain-specific code about particular types of
plots lives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawing&lt;/strong&gt;: Given those Artists and view limits for the axes,
figures out how to scale them, and where to place the ticks,
labels and other pieces of text.  This phase also includes
decimating or downscaling the data for display, since how to do
so is dependent on the limits.  Newer features such as &amp;quot;tight
limits&amp;quot; also need to happen during this phase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rendering&lt;/strong&gt;: Converts a series of simple commands from the drawing
phase into the native commands understood by a particular GUI
framework or file format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In normal interactive use, the &lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt; phase happens once, but the
&lt;strong&gt;Drawing&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Rendering&lt;/strong&gt; phases happen in a continuous loop as
the figure is panned, zoomed and resized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Drawing&lt;/strong&gt; phase comprises a great deal of Python and C++ code
&lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, much of it at the heart of what matplotlib is.  The big pieces
are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ticking (i.e. deciding where the numeric values and gridlines
should go) is a surprisingly involved task, and matplotlib's
ticking is very flexible, supporting many different scales (such
as log scale) and formats (controlling the precision of the
values, for example).  Because of this, the &lt;strong&gt;Drawing&lt;/strong&gt; phase
is dependent on matplotlib's transformation infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simplification and downsampling is performed on-the-fly as the
data is zoomed to reduce unnecessary drawing and make the
interactivity much snappier.  Of course, when it comes to large
data there are other issues about the network bandwidth and the
memory efficiency of the data representation within the browser
that may be limiting relative to what matplotlib can do now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text layout, including math text layout, is done at this stage,
because the size of the text relative to other items can not
be known until draw time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's obvious that the &lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt; phase can remain on the server.  And
the &lt;strong&gt;Rendering&lt;/strong&gt; phase can remain on the server for the native GUI
backends and the file formats.  We may need to write a &amp;quot;web browser&amp;quot;
backend, but that could be written in pure JavaScript if necessary.
It's that big &lt;strong&gt;Drawing&lt;/strong&gt; piece in the middle that has to exist
sometimes on the server and sometimes on the client.  Ideally, this
code would not be duplicated, run both in CPython and in the web
browser (depending on usage) and remain as flexible and easy to read
as the Python code we already have.  Are you starting to understand
why this is a hard problem yet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to follow this blog post up with some experiments into various
possible solutions over the upcoming days and weeks.  In the meantime,
I encourage all the comments and help on this I can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;It's easy enough to see what code is required for the drawing
phase by using &lt;cite&gt;coverage.py&lt;/cite&gt; and turning it on at the start of
&lt;cite&gt;Figure.draw&lt;/cite&gt; and turning it off again at the end.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="matplotlib"></category></entry></feed>